A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Middle East and Africa, Office Files of Betty Skolnick FA1544
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Middle East and Africa, Office Files of Betty Skolnick
1970-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Skolnick, Betty P.
Ford Foundation
FA1544
1.41 Cubic Feet 3 LGL size Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the staff subject files Betty Skolnick created during her time in the Ford Foundation's Middle East and Africa Program (MEA). Between 1973 and 1975, Skolnick served in the MEA, first as a Training Associate and then as an Assistant Program Officer. Materials within the collection document her assistance on Foundation projects aimed at supporting language development research. Records such as correspondence, memos, notes, reports, articles, and brochures show the Foundation's interest in engaging and promoting research regarding language in education, language policy and planning, and linguistics. This research primarily concerns language development in African countries such as Nigeria and Tanzania. Some records document the Foundation's grant support to institutions in African countries for development oriented language research and training.
There are also a couple of general files within the collection that mainly contain the interoffice correspondence of the Lagos, Nigeria and the Nairobi, Kenya Field Offices.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of one series.
Original order was maintained as much possible.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1970-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:052.
Biographical / Historical
Between 1970 and 1975, Betty Skolnick held several different positions within the Ford Foundation's International Division. Originally hired as a Secretary for the Latin America and the Caribbean Program, she moved to the Office for Asia and the Pacific in 1971. Then in 1973, she moved to the Middle East and Africa Program (MEA) where she would remain until she left the Foundation in 1975. She worked first as a Training Associate before becoming an Assistant Program Officer in 1974.
A significant amount of Skolnick's activities during the time she worked in the MEA concerned the Foundation's support of language development research. She helped Education Adviser Melvin Fox write the Ford Foundation report "Language in Education: Problems and Prospects in Research and Training".
Skolnick graduated from Sarah Lawrence College in 1969 with a degree in French and education. She then earned her Master's degree in teaching of English as a second language from New York University in 1972.
Ford Foundation; Adult education; Africa; Curriculum planning; Distance education; Education, Bilingual; Kenya; Language and languages; Language policy; Language planning; Linguistics -- Study and teaching; Nigeria; Tanzania
- Subject files, 1970-1975; 1; 1.41 Cubic Feet About 3 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of the subject files Betty Skolnick created during her time in the Ford Foundation's Middle East and Africa Program (MEA). Files within the series mainly pertain to the work she performed in order to assist the Foundation's support of language development research. Correspondence, memos, notes, reports, and articles concern language education related topics such as bilingual education, adult literacy and education, educational materials development, and correspondence education. Similar materials document the Foundation's interest in language planning and linguistics related subjects.
  The research documented in the series generally pertains to language development in African countries. There are significant amounts of records regarding research, initiatives, and policy developments in Nigeria and Tanzania. The series also holds some evidence of Ford Foundation grant support to institutions in African countries for development oriented language research and training.
  A couple of general files from the Lagos, Nigeria and Nairobi, Kenya Field Offices appear near the end of the series. They contain interoffice correspondence and memos regarding office administration, meetings and appointments, and program activities.
  - Language - Sudan, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Language - West Africa, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Basic education and language, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adult literacy, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Extension College (ICE) - Botswana Extension College (BEC), 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tanzania - Correspondence education and adult education, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bilingual education - Public Education Program and International Division, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bilingual education, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Language acquisition - Cognitive development, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Anthropology and Language Science in Educational Development (ALSED), 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Language policy and planning, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Patricia Lee Engle - Use of the Vernacular Languages in Education: Revisited, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Lagos, Nigeria Office - General, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Nairobi, Kenya Office - General, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Center for Applied Linguistics - International Conference on the Methodology of Linguistic Surveys, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)